this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert bloomin and with me today
Evan Gillman and Doug Barth evan is an
engineer and sre with a background in
computer networks he's been building and
operating systems in hostile
environments for his entire professional
career he was formerly an SRE a pager
duty Doug is a software engineer who has
worked on systems of various sizes at
companies such as Orbitz and pager duty
he's currently an SRE it's strike he
speaks frequently about monitoring mesh
networks and failure injection Doug and
Evan welcome to software engineering
radio and thanks for having us thank you
Evan and Doug are co-authors of the book
zero trust networks building secure
systems in untrusted networks published
in 2017 and that will be the subject of
our conversation Evan would you like to
add anything to your bio that I left out
not particularly I'm currently working
on a software project called spiffy
inspire which are geared towards solving
some of the problems that we talked
about in the book that's fairly accurate
yeah ok let's come back to that because
I I'm gonna ask about tooling sure Doug
would you like to add to your bio still
at stripe doing a sorry work I work on a
team called cloud which does like
workflows and like low-level systems for
all those stripes so for me like I tend
to be in the space of like thinking
about how do you implement some of these
concepts as opposed to like you know
abstractly thinking about the problem
and its entirety if that makes sense
it does we will be talking about zero
trust networks but to get to the point
where we can have that conversation I'm
going to spend some time on some
building
concept so we can understand the problem
domain and what problem does it solve I
would like to start out with can you
describe the traditional network
architecture which is known as the
perimeter architecture yeah you know
this is kind of the the I mean even
people who are not in tech have some
familiarity with this architecture
because it's so pervasive and has been
around for so long and this this the
concept of the perimeter model or
perimeter architecture is essentially
it's it's often times like compared to a
castle and a moat where you know you
have this thing that surrounds you that
acts kind of as this protection Airy
cord and ER protection area layer and as
things pass through that layer you know
they're kind of inspected and they're
they're understood to be allowed or not
allowed or you know it acts as a
security barrier but once you get past
that security barrier there's what kind
of where all the sensitive things are
and those sensitive things themselves
that they tend to not have any like
direct protection so a lot of people
kind of call it this this kind of castle
and moat approach where the perimeter
access the moat and it is this thing
that protects the sensitive stuff on the
inside I'm another common way that folks
describe it is crunchy on the outside
and chewy on the inside I'm and we've
been doing this for a very long time
you know if it's even before the
internet was around and you know people
people have have become very familiar
with the term firewall as a result you
know it's behind the firewall or
something like this and I me even to go
so far as and not to not to drop for but
even ago so far as you know if you look
at some physical firewalls from you know
large vendors they even have a port that
says like untrust and Trust indicating
that you know the left side the SunTrust
side is kind of going out to the wild
west and then the trust side is kind of
in this protected area is that that's
you know kind of like a high-level
description of what the perimeter model
is or represents it's not to say that
that there is always one perimeter some
architectures may have multiple
parameters as you kind of get closer and
closer towards more sensitive assets but
this concept of
you know crunchy on the outside chewy on
the inside or like castle and what kind
of thing is the the overarching theme of
the perimeter model how does the concept
of trust apply in the perimeter monel
the concept of trust of the perimeter
model is essentially if you were in on
the inside you know I alluded earlier to
these firewalls they're sometimes even
labeled trusting on trust you know if
you are on the trust side of this
firewall then the assumption is that
you're supposed to be thinner and the
assumption is that you're authorized to
be there so the trust model is very much
based on your position within the
network you know if you are if you have
access to this privileged position
within the network we trust you
unequivocally and that of course has
caused problems in the past and you know
we see a lot of headlines about why and
how that poses problems I'm sure we'll
kind of get under the Nitty Gritty of
those things but that trust model is
essentially that's kind of why the book
is called zero trust networks and kind
of take a different approach and a
different idea and say well you know
perhaps perhaps we actually don't trust
you just because you're on the special
side of this device or you're on the
special part of the network just be
analogous to in my place of work I badge
myself into the office but once I'm in
the office if I could go up and start
using any computer yeah exactly and you
know actually like there's a lot of
interesting history here around how we
arrived at you know the current state
and why and you know badging into a
building is very much part of that story
when computers are big it didn't really
move you know we relied very heavily on
physical security you know you have to
get access into the building with a
badge and got to be seen and you have to
check in and this and that in order to
get into that quote perimeter of course
all of this has changed with the modern
workforce or computers or mobile people
are bringing their own devices phones
are coming in and out and all this kind
of stuff that whole idea and concept
kind of breaks on it in fact it was
literally in the past the secure
computers are in this building and we
have one fiber that comes out of this
building when we put the firewall there
and we know that anyone that's on the
inside had to have badged in or
something like that you know obviously a
you know maybe not so obviously that's
that's not really the case anymore
and this kind of evolving usage pattern
is you know something that your trust
model tries to address what does traffic
have to do to get through the perimeter
into the trusted area look think this
second jump in this kind of varies a bit
but you know usually you end up saying
that someone pokes a hole in your
perimeter right you forward a port into
some internal system or maybe you like
formalize it a bit more and you have a
DMZ subnet where you put all your
internet facing systems and then private
subnets that are you know presumably
proxy to from proxies living in the DMZ
one example of perimeter model is a VPN
explain what that is and how it fits
into the perimeter model
sure I can keep going there so VPNs like
pretty common for how people get access
to private systems you run some software
on your computer that makes a tunnel
over to another network and it's kind of
like you basically there are sending
packets through a you know encrypted
tunnel to be emitted out on the other
side inside that network as if it
originated as a device and that like
physical network presumably ignore cloud
for a bit
and so again kind of like this whole
physical access implies authorization
you would say that on a VPN and the fact
that you are able to negotiate that
tunnel meant that you should be able to
communicate widely inside the network
with no with no real like checks on
whether or not that's allowed what is
the threat model the modern networks
face this it's highly varied and of
course it depends on the company and it
depends on what you're trying to protect
and it depends on the kinds of attackers
that that you're going to see but you
know largely the big kind of
understanding and takeaway here is you
know the threats that we see now don't
have to be sitting next to you they can
be on the other side of the world people
carry devices around devices move a lot
around and so this concept of having
this kind of like stable perimeter that
is impenetrable is very very difficult
to do effectively today as a result
because it's not really that impermeable
right people are bringing things inside
and outside physically
people are poking holes in it through
this VPN stuff you know and VPN even
arose kind of from like these changing
access patterns where you know hey you
had to be in the building to use the
secure thing because that's behind the
firewall but then all of a sudden
someone's working remote and they you
know we want them to be able to continue
working so how do we emulate them being
behind this physical thing and then all
of these are kind of like half steps and
towards the direction okay
acknowledging that hey you know maybe
maybe everything is not behind this
thing or in front of this thing so in
terms of threats I mean it can be
literally anything from you know
extremely well financed attackers if you
have up if you're a high-value target
for whatever reason it it should be even
as low as what we used to call script
kiddies or you know people who are just
kind of playing around and don't even
have access to the highest technology
you know bypassing these kinds of
traditional perimeter Security's are
fairly trivial and I mean the average
teenager is is likely to understand
techniques and methods through by which
it could be bypassed so what you're
saying is that you can't rely on the
perimeter to filter out attacks and that
there can easily be things inside the
perimeter it could do damage to your
systems absolutely you know that it's
not to say that the perimeter has no
value but it is to say that you can only
go so far and the kinds of attacks that
you see today and the kinds of threats
we see today are able to bypass all of
these controls fairly trivially so
certainly you should there should not be
an assumption that everything inside is
vetted and trusted that's kind of the
premise of this whole kind of model I
have a quote from a Google program
engineer that I found I was reading
about this he said do not trust your
network it is probably already owned do
you guys agree with that yep
wait first week said what did he mean by
that I think like the thing I take from
that is if you aren't like introspecting
what's going on in your ternal network
you don't know what bad is already
lurking there all right and so
that's kind of why you never should
trust it is because it's it's like this
constant toil of cleaning up some sort
of compromise that you then remediate
there's your answer to this change or
hasn't changed for so much networking
which is now in public cloud as compared
to on Prem think so you know the the the
the the threats are very different
they're you know an on-prem it could be
someone walked up and plugged into the
side of the building you know some
exposure could be anything right you
don't really have those kinds of
problems in cloud but depending on your
provider you may have other problems
particularly when you're sending traffic
between regions perhaps across the
country or over oceans and who controls
those links and who has access to that
information the cloud platforms provide
a lot of kind of primitives security
primitives that can be leaned upon and
so the way that you go about solving
this thing is a little bit different but
I think that certainly certainly the
belief should be that it's not to say
that you're that every network out there
is probably owned right but that should
be the attitude certainly a Google scale
that is almost certainly the case right
but that should be the that should be
the general attitude because you know at
the end of the day even if it's not
owned today it might be tomorrow so you
should build with this in mind right and
it's not just that hey so it's not like
only hey somebody's plugged into my
patch panel or something something like
that it could simply be oh we have the
server over here that serves up you know
a Status page or something silly and we
forgot to update it and it's exposed to
the Internet and someone was able to get
in and the fact that they were able to
get into that one server which is you
know behind the perimeter in this
trusted area essentially means that they
are in your network so even if even if
you are not on today you should
certainly take the stamps that you are
because I mean any system online long
enough will eventually suffer one of
these problems we've been talking about
up to this point about the traditional
network architecture which you believe
is fatally flawed I'd like to now
introduce the concept of zero trust
model what does that mean
to place a zero trust in your network
and so we um when we were at the book I
think we had like five points which I've
at this point forgotten a lot of them
but we tried to lay out what exactly
zero trust networks would mean so it's
things like all network traffic is
encrypted you have like some pre
knowledge of what types of flows should
exist inside that network you have to
authenticate devices and users and
applications individually but I think
like the way you should really think
about it when you zoom out is you start
from this standpoint of if you believe
that your network is probably already
owned what do you actually want that
network to be responsible for and you
almost certainly do not want it to be
responsible for ensuring that your
traffic is secure and authorized you
probably just want to like task it with
shipping bits around and then you layer
on the like identity and authorization
like at the endpoints Evan do you have
anything to add yeah you know it took us
a while to come up with a name for the
book you know at the end of the day we
wanted to describe this kind of
different way of thinking the way of
thinking that was different than what
people have been doing in the last few
decades them you know we ended up on
zero trust networks because it was the
moat it was the most descriptive name
that we could think of believe it or not
like it and and I believe the subtitle
of the book is building building secure
systems and untrusted networks and
that's kind of exactly what we're
talking about right we're talking about
how do you how you go from having a few
hosts that need to communicate with each
other in such a way that it doesn't
really matter what happens in the middle
you know an attacker can be positioned
anywhere between those two hosts and the
security primitives will still stand so
we call a zero trust networks because it
is to say we don't place any trust into
the network we don't trust the network
to perform to properly perform any kind
of enforcement or confidentiality
functions instead we kind of push all
that as Douglas saying push all that out
to the endpoint this is a principle
called the end-to-end principle which
basically says the network should do
what is good for it should ship packets
from one place to another place
it shouldn't be necessarily so involved
in inspecting and scrubbing and securing
and providing you know assurances that
the source IP is accurate and so on and
so forth I mean that perimeter model to
give an example a database gets a
connection request from an app server
and say well the app server it's behind
the firewall so I'll accept the incoming
request but in their trust network the
criteria are gonna be much tougher than
that as whether it should accept the
request or not is that correct yeah
absolutely you know if you're saying if
the database is saying hey you're behind
this perimeter so I will accept the
request you know it's kind of going back
to say well what else is behind that
perimeter there's probably more than
just a web server it's not unlikely that
there's an attacker back there also
should you really be allowing requests
from anything and if you take if you
think of there's like a long you know
established principle called lease
privilege the system should be
implemented to be authorized to do only
the things that they must absolutely
need to do in order to get their job
done and so if you think about that an
extended towards the network you know
it's very similar like probably only the
application server should be essence
accessing the database server so you
know we put policies in place and we put
security controls in place that you know
go as far as is reasonable to ensure
that that's the case and the fact that
is behind the perimeter is not of any
significant bearing in terms of deciding
whether it should be accepted or not in
your book you present design of the zero
trust Network consisting of three I have
it broken down into three components
maybe this is for OB user authentication
application authentication device
authentication and Trust scoring let's
group all of these types of
authentication
together what do you mean by
authentication of these different
entities that live on the network sure
so the you know we talk about a
syndication we're trying to basically
answer the question are
you who you say you are so users pretty
straightforward because we kind of deal
with that every day right it's like
commonly a username and password maybe
you get a little fancy and you start
bringing like security keys into
consideration here or you do like what
is it like time-based one-time the top
thing that I can't remember what the
acronym is top P hot B yeah you bring in
like a second factor code right but like
the whole point of authentication is
simply saying like can we positively
assert that you are who you say you are
we split them out into three different
taxis because I think they all kind of
get authenticated in subtly different
ways
like I said users username password
maybe a second factor but once you start
talking about like devices then you're
doing usually like some sort of
certificate that someone's provisioned
onto your instance or if you want to get
really fancy maybe your computer has
like a TPM chip in it and you have some
sort of secure boot system so you've
routed it in hardware as opposed to like
some credentials that could be
exfiltrated off that box it's trust when
it's granted it's time limited yeah so
that was one of the things that we
wanted to really call it is that in a
zero trust network like that there's
like a time component to all of this
like authorization decision that needs
to be considered in your designs and not
even just like time base but also like
action based like how do you like the
big question is how do you build a
network that can provide some measure
protection against novel attacks and so
one way you might do that is you might
like kind of fuzzy the like
authorization line to say like well we
have this this concept of a score which
is a magical number that tells us how
much we should trust you and we might
just like set you know if you are
falling in your trust score we might ask
for extra authorization just to make
sure that you're not some malicious
actor trying to like leverage your
position on an endpoint to to do
malicious things essentially so how is a
trust score calculated and by who and
what does it goes into it yeah that's a
great question so um so to be like
totally upfront like trust scoring and
engines I feel like it's a very
forward-thinking concept that
there's not a whole lot of detailed
implementations for like broadly
speaking you'd probably want a system
that is receiving events of activities
and then using that to derive a score
like if we want to get fancy maybe you
could say like something machine
learning is going and throwing a thrill
model and dumping out a score in the end
that's you know it's kind of like what
your credit card does very where it's
looking at transactional activities to
decide whether or not you look
fraudulent but that's all very hand wavy
right because we're just saying like
some magic model somewhere gives us a
number that we have decided we trust
yeah I would like to just maybe kind of
color that in a little bit more you know
their varying kind of levels of
intensity of this stuff you know it can
a lot of it comes down to the probably
behavior based and what things look like
in the past and baselines and things
along those lines but to kind of pull it
back and make things a little more real
like most people see this on a day to
day basis most people see this regularly
with kind of anomaly detection based on
like logins for online services so you
know if you've ever like maybe you know
you always look at Twitter from
California or something and then you
know one day you got on a plane I went
to try and an or I guess if that example
whether you got on the plane went
somewhere to some other country and then
you tried to log into Twitter and
Twitter says hold on this looks weird
you know we sent you an email
verification we want to make sure that
this is actually you that's a great
example of this thing in action where
they've looked at past behavior and
they've said this particular event is
kind of fishy and you want to some extra
assurance you know we call it trust
score in the book but you know the
flipside to trust is risk and so you
know you could you know I still kind of
alluded to you can call it like a risk
risk score as well fraud detection
systems often implement these kinds of
algorithms so it's it's maybe a you know
we have some practice doing this and
there are some companies out there who
have pioneered applying this principle
to computer access and computer
authorization systems but perhaps it's a
well understood idea with a novel
application so to try to put an example
on this
in the more rigid policy based framework
I'm logging in a prison username
password maybe an RSA key okay I'm good
it's all correct but this trust scoring
you might look at well I've now logged
in a hundred times in the last three
minutes from IP addresses in Hungary
China and California that's a little
weird and it's hard to explain how
Robert could have gotten from Hungary to
China in three minutes or less so that's
gonna impact my trust score negatively
and maybe I need a 500 to get into the
system I want to get into and I got
docked 200 points for these weird
anomalies so that's I'm not going to get
in to the system am I getting the story
yeah that's exactly what it is you know
and and and it's taking that and it's
saying even further like you know we can
apply the same principles to like access
patterns inside the data center you know
from workload or workload or service to
service as well it doesn't just have to
be user logins so going back to then the
database it's getting a connection from
the app server you would apply this same
philosophy of scoring what is normal
usage for an app server versus some kind
of anomalies that maybe it's not an app
server it's some malicious actor that's
trying to attack the database and it's
managed to obtain the credentials
belonging to an AB server yeah
absolutely and you know it transcends
just like access patterns there's a lot
more to it you know and and briefly
touched upon earlier about
authenticating devices and users or
devices and apps you know these things
are done kind of in tandem so it's not
just knowing that it's the app server
but it's about knowing hey it was an app
server that connected to me
and I know that it was the Apache web
server in particular on that portray or
that is connecting to me and those two
things together give a much higher
degree of assurance and it can be you
know in terms of calculating the score
it may not just be you know the
historical access patterns of this
Apache web server but it could also be
hey we know we know the identity of the
apps are rebirthing
running on and we know it hasn't been
patched in six months and so perhaps
that dings the score trust score or risk
score right because it is now more risky
to accept connections from this machine
that hasn't been patched what I think
you're saying Urban's is there's almost
unlimited range of things you could take
into account in the score and it's not
just you get scored on each thing
independently but multiple things
independent variables which might be
each one okay on their own but together
don't make sense or sort of vector
combinations of things could go into the
score yeah exactly that yep
okay want to move on to another concept
in his ear twist network the idea of the
control plane and the data plane explain
what those are and how do they interact
sure you want to take this Duggar slide
sure I can take it so I think basically
what we were trying to tease out there
is when you think about the architecture
of this system you should be very
cognizant of the control plane being
like the set of systems that ultimately
make the decision of whether or not
something should be trusted and have the
access to manage the rest of the network
and the data plane is like the bits of
like control software that you sprinkle
throughout the network that the control
plane is like reconfiguring so maybe to
put this in terms of like something
that's very hot and buzz wordy right now
would be like envoy and service meshes
they generally have like a proxy that
runs on every instance and you route
network traffic through it but you
usually have this suite of applications
that sit off the instance that are like
configuring each proxy is like a big
distributed system and so those like
separate systems are the control plane
and the data plane is like each
individual envoy proxy right and the the
most common kind of component that you
put in the data plane we usually call
like an enforcement point so you know
you have this control plane which is
making all these decisions and enforcing
all this policy but at some point you
have to have the traffic cop sort of
speak which comes in and actually blocks
or disallows or allows and it's these
kind of traffic cops that sit inside the
data plane
so one analogy here could be you know
like traffic control systems on roads
and cities there's oftentimes
centralized computer systems which can
coordinate you know traffic lights and
things like this across a across a town
or a city and then you have the traffic
lights themselves that in this case the
data plane are the roads and the traffic
lights are sitting in the data plane
actually making the enforcement and
controlling the traffic in the flow and
then you have this control plane which
is the separate computer system which is
instructing the traffic lights on what
they should do if the app server wants
to talk to the database server then does
traffic have to get permitted by the
control plane in order for that
connection to be made it depends on the
implementation the control plan can play
a very active role in this but in
practice that can be hard to scale them
in terms of like performance overhead
unavailability impact of requiring these
services to be there all the time in
order for anything to function usually
what we see is kind of like a
half-and-half approach where maybe we
cache some decisions inside the data
plane or we use the control plane to
push down configuration or state into
the data plane that can kind of survive
on its own for some time in case it's
severed from the control plane so you
know some people may some people may
prefer to not do that because they want
more active control when it comes to the
cost so at an example be something like
single sign-on where you obtain a token
from an authentication server with a
time limit and then you can present that
to a number of resources in the network
yeah it could be another example might
be hey you know my control plane has
configured the firewalls inbound and how
about firewalls on both of these
instances because it knows the IP
addresses you know maybe those changed
over time but the control plane has to
be up to do that but if the control
plane goes down and the steady state
remains maybe additionally the control
plane has pushed down and dropped
certificates on to these machines that
they use for authenticating each other
and those certificates similar to the
token
good for some period of time so you know
the control plate has kind of informed
the data plan of its position and what
should be allowed and not allowed and
and in some configurations I would say
that most configurations the data thing
kind of sail along for some period of
time without control plate and
involvement I want to move on and talk
about encryption you mentioned that
earlier if you don't trust the network
then you need to encrypt all the traffic
that goes across the network then are
all conversations between servers or
services on the network encrypted using
em TLS yep pretty much and one of the
things I find fascinating about this is
it's not just about like you're not
trusting the network to to like divulge
the traffic but also sometimes you just
don't trust the network to deliver that
traffic faithfully like I've literally
had this happen in my job where we've
had bit flips that caused problems in
like transit and so it's not just a
mythical thing that could happen it's a
thing that like causes you problems if
you don't have that kind of like guard
against just malicious activity or
accidental like rewriting of traffic
yeah the the encryption is not strictly
but practically always provides a degree
of authenticity to the traffic so you'll
get to know if it was modified because
those things will be invalidated so you
know that that's a really important
aspect and you know it doesn't have to
be mutually authenticated TLS that is
one of the more popular options today
but you know in the book we wrote about
doing this with IPSec and there's new
protocols out there one that comes to
mind is wire guard certainly there are a
lot of different options to accomplish
this kind of encryption and you know
which of those you choose is is a little
bit new Austin's aware and the staff do
you want it to lie
what kind of keys and types of
authentication do you want it to be able
to be capable of things along those
lines but but but mutually authenticated
TLS has taken a front seat and in the
last couple years certainly we have a
show which is going to be published
before this one on TLS and PKR which is
the public key infrastructure
and that so we went a lot of detail into
the public certificate authorities if
you're running TLS on your own network
do you run your own certificate
authority within your organization yeah
that's definitely what we recommend I
think it makes the most sense so yeah
it's it's they can be difficult to
manage and in the last couple of years
there's been quite a bit of effort in
the open source world to to make those
privately managed PK eyes a little bit
easier to wrangle and reason about and
they're certainly the the advised path
simply because the flexibility of public
CA is as public CAS or you know really
their bread and butter is like web
systems where you have you know not
necessarily anonymous users but you have
users coming in from perhaps anywhere
that are not part of that organization
you can think of like you know securing
the connection to your banking website
or something when we talk about zero
trust networks we don't it is very very
difficult perhaps impossible to apply
that concept to the open Internet
consumers at large it's way more geared
towards enterprises and companies which
can control the systems and know exactly
what is supposed to be happening and
when and where and so you know the goal
in life and the purpose of the public CA
system even though they give they
provide PKI and give certificates
there's not really built with these
kinds of usages in mind and so now the
flexibility can can be problematic where
are some of the challenges in running
your own internal CA key management is
certainly one when you run an internal
CA the an internal PKI
you know there's a nation that you're
holding a very powerful keys and and
there's this kind of idea of a route and
that's that like the CA and if that key
is compromised that all else is
cauterized so managing that key of
securing it appropriately can be very
difficult that's the first problem their
first challenge the second challenge is
that these certificates that are
generated by the PKI that represent the
identities
they're time-limited and renewing them
can be very difficult that they're very
you know this is one of the projects
that I'm working on is automating this
you know a lot of the issue as today is
pretty this fairly manual and pushing
those certificates out and updating them
can be extremely painful and extremely
expensive so what people tend to do is
make them last a very long time which is
also not a great solution so and then
when they come to expire maybe you
forget and the thing falls over or or
maybe you have to dig out some playbook
that dust it off of the shelf you know
and figure out how to do this thing once
every year or two years or however often
you have to do it and because these
these processes can be expensive you
tend to use them limited fashion so you
might pick and choose where where you
install them or maybe there's only one
or something you start to cut corners
because they're expensive to issue and
manage so that limited lifetime and the
issuance the secure and automated
issuance of those certificates is the
second very large challenge with that if
you're routing requests through your
network over HTTPS and it's encrypted
does that make life more difficult for
proxies or load balancers like nginx so
I think maybe this depends on what the
purpose of the proxy is if we're talking
about like are you imagining a proxy
which intersects encrypted traffic to
the side whether or not it's suspicious
yeah that would make it harder I mean
some organizations do like TLS enter
interception where they like give the
keys to the proxy tier in order for it
to unwrap and inspect the traffic but I
think that's quite honestly kind of
falling out of favor and in preference
of asking a proxy very explicitly to
route traffic out to say the Internet
and you just get it kind of like the
domain level coming into your network I
don't really see too many problems
personally curious what you think of it
yeah I mean it there is like a fairly
large installed user base of you know
what we call middle boxes these are
things put in the network that argument
to intercept traffic perhaps for passive
inspection
for a prep for active manipulation this
has been a pretty common pattern
particularly in enterprise for
exfiltration detection and things along
these lines as Doug said though you know
I think it might from my perspective the
trend in the industry is very much we
probably shouldn't be doing that and you
know maybe it was a great idea when we
started but now that you know what we
are ended up seeing is that and I'll
give you an example of you know TLS
which is the same as SSL or HTTPS
one-point-three is designed as a busser
boosted security features and now we're
seeing as we're seeing an effort by a
lot of the manufacturers and users of
these middleboxes to kind of weaken and
water down the protocol such that it can
permit the interception and inspection
of this traffic by these middle boxes
and that's certainly in tension with
what we're trying to do is in direct
tension you know these encryption these
encryption protocols are exactly
designed to prevent this kind of
interception and inspection of
manipulation so the caught the very
concept that perhaps we want to permit
it but only in certain limited use cases
feels a lot to me like you know the
government should have a backdoor to the
encryption argument you know so that is
kind of the battle that is continues to
be waged but you know I think in general
is particularly unlike them were
forward-looking tech companies in
particular definitely kind of trying
their best to move away from that
pattern and install end-to-end
encryption instead in your book you have
entire chapter on trusting devices
chapter on trusting users and one on
trusting apps we're not gonna have time
to delve into all those I want to talk a
little bit about trusting apps a couple
of interesting issues there one is the
idea of doing security scans on apps can
you explain what what that is what are
you scanning for how do you scan sure so
like at the basic level you might
imagine something like what in Ruby land
you have bundler audit which goes
through your gem file list and make sure
you're not running dependencies that
have known CVEs on them it's pretty
basic maybe you like step it up a notch
and start doing like fuzzing of
applications automatically
or you have some sort of like linting
system which is you know it's a web
application is it taking user data and
jamming it into a sequel query things
like that it's really just essentially
like in a lot of ways automating the
auditing practices that like a security
engineer would do for your applications
and making sure that that's like
continuously being checked and giving
people early feedback I mean it could be
anything from from static analysis like
this Douglas thing to active analysis
like fuzzing and you know the goal of
which to automate and build all this
until I like to release pipelines and
stuff like that there's kind of a
practice that is a buzzword that has
kind of come come to fruition called dev
sac ops which is a lot of it is focused
on this kind of concept of securing the
pipeline and ensuring that we understand
when vulnerabilities are introduced we
can catch them before they're released
or very very quickly after they're
released in the worst case we we didn't
have a whole show on dev suck-ups and I
may come back to that bit later could
you
you mentioned fuzzing what do you what
do you mean by fuzzing in this context I
said in this context it could be you
know my my CI pipeline compiles the app
and starts it and then we have fuzzers
that run against the API endpoints at
that hop exposes and we run them for
some time before we release it or after
we merge things in the master or stuff
like that but to ensure that we haven't
introduced anything funny yep and so
like if people don't know fuzzers right
are like sending essentially random data
to endpoints to see if it crashes is the
usual like pattern here mm-hmm
or the return code changes or some some
signal that the input was meaningful in
some way okay another discussion in the
chapter on apps was this build pipeline
we've so far been assuming that app
server that if I could verify it is
really the app server that I the
database should accept the connection
from it but you you point out that
different kinds of attacks could get
into the build chain how do we build a
trusted solid executable yeah that's
it's it's a difficult question
you know frankly very few projects have
been able to kind of reach that level of
maturity that there are we do know of
techniques we wrote about some of them
in the book some of them I can't work I
can't remember the technical term of it
but the reproducible builds is one right
that's the term and this is a
reproducible build is to say from this
commit in the source code every single
time I build it I will end up with a
binary with the exact same saw stone the
exact same binary that forbid this is a
very very powerful concept because it
means that I can go from source code to
verified output without necessarily
having to trust the thing that that
brought the source code to the output so
for instance if I had a CI CD pipeline
that was delivering applications or
delivering artifacts if that pipeline
was owned and compromised and something
was injected into this process to open
up a back door or something like that
its detectable with a reproducible bill
because I could simply run the build on
my laptop and see that I got a different
shot for that thing from that particular
commit and I can know that it was
influenced along the way you may have
you may have observer machines which are
watching the artifacts of doing their
own builds and verifying that this build
is accurate and correct and you know
it's a timely question because I think
just earlier this week there was a
fairly popular and old software project
that was discovered to have a
compromised CI CD system and had been
compromised for many months and the
attackers were able to inject a backdoor
into that binary and the developers had
no idea because that backdoor was not in
the source code and when there seems the
when they received the notification from
the researcher that something was up
there was very confusing so this is a
very very powerful attack vector that is
becoming more and more common with
people in the know and as related
perhaps all statists of software supply
chain attacks which is also becoming
very common unfortunately so all of
these things are kind of related to
having confidence in the build we've got
an example of supply chain attack be if
someone's able to gain control of a git
repo and inject something malicious into
an open source library that happens to
be a dependency of something that you're
using and so
pull it in with maven or one lorry yep
exactly and one of the more common ones
that we're seeing now is with Ruby you
know the the ruby gems website which
distributes gems people will you know
take over accounts and on push new gen
releases up with your backdoored and
then your project pulls it in and all of
a sudden oh nice I won't move on to
discussion about the role of DevOps and
infrastructure as code in Xero networks
I believe from the book that this
concept
the infrastructure is code influenced
your approach to zero choice networks is
that correct and how so yeah so I think
the way that we kind of approached our
own personal networks as we used
infrastructure as code systems like chef
as like the like the spot where we grew
up a system before we actually took it
out and extract it and do a different
system I know Evan did some work with
like pulling out the firewall management
control plane essentially into a
dedicated system but it initially
started it's just like chef cookbooks
that were a lot smarter than average and
I think like the the kind of broad
lesson here is that when you start
looking at these zero trust networks a
lot of the the configuration is
automated and reacting to like changing
membership in the network and so you
just have to automate the process you
can't like task people with setting this
up there's also you know an angle where
infrastructure is coded as similar
patterns have enabled this kind of
approach to security being so tight and
being rape highly reactive of being able
to very finely control these attributes
over a large number of systems and the
passes then completely cumbersome and
you know I think you know we talked a
little bit in the book about how
automation in general has made this kind
of pervasive security posture possible
where in the past you know we want to in
the past it was well we want to reduce
the number of systems that are exposed
to the absolute bare minimum so that we
can control them tightly and put a lot
of focus on them and well
still true you know the the reason some
but perhaps some of the reasoning for
doing so no longer holes because hey now
like we can actually ensure that the
same posture is applied across so much
larger fleet we could do it an automated
fashion or we could do it in a way that
is audible and observable I think the
concept of preventing drift would figure
in because if some malware just a person
didn't know any better has gone and
changed something in broken security
that you can always revert to known good
state by running your configuration
management or provisioning systems
absolutely so say I wanted to get
started on this is do have to burn it
all down and build it from scratch or
can perimeter Network evolve in this
direction by making some incremental
changes yeah I don't think you have to
burn it all down I would not recommend
you do that I think like my perspective
is you if you have a perimeter network
you basically start like downplaying the
amount of trust that you have inside
that network and start building up
systems that are much more like
pervasive right so let's take an example
let's say you got a perimeter where you
had no on host firewall system that went
up if all your network is being shipped
over the network unencrypted figure out
some path to like encrypting that
Network maybe it's mutual TLS and a
service mesh or maybe it's IPSec and and
fanciness there but just kind of like
start somewhere probably start at the
systems that have the sensitive data
because that's what people are
ultimately trying to get access to and
like radiate outward from that point
yeah exactly that's not a really like an
interesting thing is that you know you
build the security outwards you know
rather than inwards previously with the
perimeter model you say hey here's the
pipe that comes out of the building and
I'm going to start there and put my
firewall and then as I as things go and
I'm going to kind of build inwards
towards them put more maybe more
firewalls or controls but closer that
you get towards your more sensitive
systems this kind of like takes that in
terms of owner's heavens as well you
should be starting from the most
sensitive systems and kind of like
building and pushing that security
words it is not mutually exclusive with
perimeter firewalls and we probably
recommend that you keep those around but
perhaps they are not the primary line of
defense or the first line of defense or
anything along that we've talked some
about this component of the network the
trust engine and it could be doing
fairly sophisticated machine learning
behavioral scoring are there any open
source projects that I could use to -
for that component I have not seen any I
know of some commercial implementations
and I know of some in-house
implementations I don't I'm not aware of
any open source projects focusing on the
closest thing that we have our open
source projects focusing on
authorization and policy there's one
project in particular called the open
policy agent or OPA and this project is
geared towards that enforcement layer
give it a policy give it some input and
it can make a decision but as far as the
scoring goes I'm not aware of any and if
you wanted to use open in conjunction
with such a system you would have to
provide it with this score what do you
like to talk about some of the tools or
projects that you're contributing to in
this area and what they do sure you know
I've been spending my topper we wrote
the book you know it was kind of a weird
weird feeling because you know the
motivation for writing it was show folks
a different way to think about this
problem maybe show like a different
paradigm right and get them thinking in
a way that that is perhaps a lot
different or a little or a lot different
than the way that they had been thinking
before and perhaps light a path forward
right but you know having published it
and looking back it was I don't want to
say a failure but it was certainly you
know we began to realize hey you know
we've just told them that there's this
totally different way of thinking about
things and oh by the way like there's
very few options out there you know good
luck have fun building at
so I kind of been on personal vendetta
of trying trying to trying to provide
some building blocks that are useful to
building these kinds of networks so the
project I've been working on for the
past couple years it's called spiffy and
there's a related project called spire
and those two projects are aimed at
getting identity into work loads so you
know when we say everything else we
authenticated and encrypted you know in
order to authenticate something you have
to have some notion of identity and in
order to encrypt you have to have some
keys or credentials that go along with
that so the software project I work on
is related to standardizing this notion
of identity and providing automated
issuance of certificates and an
automated PKI deployment I know we
discussed previously some of those
challenges of key management and
challenges around automated issuance of
certificates this is the focus of the
project yes I don't have to do quite as
much I'm generally a consumer of these
technologies so for me day in day out
I'm working on things like console does
some of this type of concept where they
have like console Connect and they'll do
they will essentially spit up like envoy
proxies for you and make it relatively
easy for you to have mutual TLS inside
your network although I haven't used
that particular product yet also you
know terraform a lot of the hashey Corp
stuff I tend to deal with day-in day-out
but again similar opportunities for
improving the stay of the world like at
some point I want to get to a state
where say like our terraform
configuration runs through a policy
agent to check to make sure that people
are you know telling us when they're
spending money is like a you know
somewhat tangential zero trust thing but
it's you know still related you know we
went from when the book was published to
having very few projects if any
available in the open realm open source
wrote a few years later that story has
changed about sure there are quite a few
projects which are aimed towards
building blocks and providing some
foundation that you can kind of build on
top of but there's still quite a ways to
go and a lot of room for new
some improvement and I'm always looking
for collaborators if anyone's interested
where do you think we are in the
adoption curve of this philosophy
unfortunately is after the book was
published this whole concept of your
trust has become very buzz wording
different people that it's kind of
similar to how DevOps used to be like
different people think of it in
different ways and have different
definitions of what it is and isn't
different people have said well my
product does that or my product does
this and that's your trust and sometimes
it is sometimes it isn't in terms of
adoption I what I'm seeing in the field
is folks who are beginning to kind of
take this task off we've gotten to the
point where people have said yeah this
sounds about right this sounds like the
direction we should be going and some
people are saying well how do I do that
some people are biting the bullet and
saying okay we're gonna start some
people are kind of in the middle of the
journey very few people have actually
reached the end of that journey or have
reached a state that we would call
something that is close to zero trust so
you know perhaps were and kind of like
the hype phase and maybe just a little
bit past it would be my guess yeah I was
gonna say like are we talking adopt we
talking hype because if I were to like
peg hype I would say where we're still
going up so we haven't gotten to any
sort of inflated expectations too too
far yet DVD your book do you have a case
study of something called the beyond
Corp Network which Google published was
that a reference architecture and then
you could try to build something along
the same lines or was it more like an
open source project that they distribute
and you can download and start using
pieces of it so Google's beyond Corp is
definitely more on the reference
architecture side they don't as far as I
know they don't open source any of their
their systems but like it's a I think if
you were to say Google is like an early
innovator here you know there you are
saying that their network got to a point
where they would not trust it and what's
the point even of having that perimeter
we should just expose it to the Internet
yeah and they I know they've productized
some of it in Google cloud but they have
not released it as any kind of
comprehensive project or so anything
that you can really down-low
it was certain they were certainly
pioneers in this area frankly you know
Doug and I were working on working on
systems that that threw away the same
assumptions and we're working on systems
that have very similar property ISM to
be honest it wasn't until we read the
beyond court papers that we realized
that there was kind of a larger story
here
you know we've read what they were doing
and we thought hey you know we're we're
doing stuff that sounds a lot like that
but it's applied in a different way and
you know there's something more here
than just beyond corporate just what we
built and so that was kind of the
impetus to you know do some more
research talk to some more people we
delivered a few conference talks on
those lives and ultimately wrote the
book with a lot of the insights that we
gained from you know our own
implementations and experience as well
as talking to some of the folks who run
beyond court one final question I have I
couldn't really figure this out myself
so in Amazon Amazon's Cloud they have a
concept of security groups I can set up
a security group and add certain
instances which are virtual machines to
security group a then I can explicitly
allow traffic from security group a over
port safe port 443 to security Group B
is that more of a perimeter network with
these zones or is that really more of a
zero trust concept or somewhere in
between I think if we were to pick like
terms that the Evans that it's kind of
like micro segmentation would be the
term you might consider where you say
that you have these like very small
firewalls that are just doing packet
filtering and so it's definitely a
better step than simply saying at the
perimeter we allow Internet access from
these ports and then everything inside
is wide open but I don't know that it
gets you down to like that a true
identity of the you know the originator
of traffic inside your network yeah and
there can be there can be kind of
disconnects if you know you're talking
across different regions you know we're
talking to different clouds or those two
things don't plug into each
there and certainly security groups
don't provide any kind of encryption or
wire confidentiality so you know if
you're talking across long weeks into
region or across continents you know
that's there's fairly wide exposure that
you're having and so you know I think
like bit it security groups take a step
in the right direction you know they
bring you out of the world of thinking
about IP addresses and into the world of
thinking about what is my intent and how
do I want I connect these things and
having an automated system under the
covers that is enacting those policies
and enforcing those things as the system
changes so certainly a step in the right
direction I did and you know but a code
it doesn't it doesn't quite go all the
way there but it's certainly better than
than what we have been doing and just
like be very clear right like security
groups when applied using best practices
go you bring it a step in our direction
right like if you just made the security
group and jammed it on everyone didn't
really help anything but if you do like
each you know machine-type gets its own
security group and you're actually like
encoding who should be talking to whom
then you get some benefit okay let's
wrap things up Evan I will link to
spiffy and spire in the show notes Evan
would you like to give out any other
places on the internet where people
could follow or find you even my handle
is Evan UVA and two six four five I'm
pretty findable on Twitter I also hang
out and if you're linking to a spiffy
inspired projects I hang out in that
slack channel and feel free to reach out
to me there and I'm on LinkedIn and all
the other things that you would normally
expect I love hearing from people so
please don't feel shy Doug yeah for me
Twitter Doug Barth kept it simple
usually you'll get out either random
security stuff or a lot of dad jokes
great thank you both very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
this has been Robert blumen thank you
for listening thank you thank you Robert
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by at
your police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se Radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening